<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2013-02-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Sky v0.2.3 Released</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/sky-v0-2-3.html"/>
    <id>/blog/sky-v0-2-3.html</id>
    <published>2013-02-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-02-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;#39;s New?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sky version 0.2.3 has been released.
You can download it from the main &lt;a href="/"&gt;Sky web site&lt;/a&gt;.
We&amp;#39;ve added a UI and a JavaScript tracker to the Sky ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The official Sky UI is called &lt;a href="/docs/skybox.html"&gt;Skybox&lt;/a&gt;.
It&amp;#39;s a Sinatra + D3.js application that allows you to analyze the flow of actions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;#39;s New?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sky version 0.2.3 has been released.
You can download it from the main &lt;a href="/"&gt;Sky web site&lt;/a&gt;.
We&amp;#39;ve added a UI and a JavaScript tracker to the Sky ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The official Sky UI is called &lt;a href="/docs/skybox.html"&gt;Skybox&lt;/a&gt;.
It&amp;#39;s a Sinatra + D3.js application that allows you to analyze the flow of actions.
It&amp;#39;s a first cut at the UI so it&amp;#39;s simple but big things are coming for Skybox!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A JavaScript tracking server called &lt;a href="/docs/skycap.html"&gt;Skycap&lt;/a&gt; has been added so you can directly track actions and state from a simple JavaScript import.
Many thanks to the guys at &lt;a href="http://segment.io"&gt;Segment.IO&lt;/a&gt; for helping with the JavaScript API.
Skycap&amp;#39;s interface is based on the &lt;a href="https://github.com/segmentio/analytics.js"&gt;Analytics.js&lt;/a&gt; API.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;#39;s Next&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sky v0.2.4 will be the last planned release before a large v0.3.0 release which will include multi-node distribution so you can cluster your Sky servers.
The Sky server will see time-based sampling added so you can specify a query time (e.g. 500 ms) and Sky will query as much as it can within that time.
We&amp;#39;ll also be adding worker pooling and some other performance improvements so you can scale Sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skybox will see filtering, segmentation and back references added so you can drill into your data and break it up by different types of users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have also been many requests for more details about how Sky works and how the query engine works.
I&amp;#39;ll be adding some D3.js visualizations to the Sky web site to help explain it.
If you have any requests for blog post topics or you want to know more about Sky, &lt;a href="mailto:sky@librelist.com"&gt;e-mail the mailing list&lt;/a&gt; and suggest it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sky v0.2.3 Released</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/sky-v0-2-2.html"/>
    <id>/blog/sky-v0-2-2.html</id>
    <published>2013-01-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-01-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;#39;s New?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sky version 0.2.3 has been released.
You can download it from the main &lt;a href="/"&gt;Sky web site&lt;/a&gt;.
We&amp;#39;ve added a command line importer, overhauled the query system and fixed a bunch of bugs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new query interface has been added!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;#39;s New?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sky version 0.2.3 has been released.
You can download it from the main &lt;a href="/"&gt;Sky web site&lt;/a&gt;.
We&amp;#39;ve added a command line importer, overhauled the query system and fixed a bunch of bugs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A new query interface has been added!
The Lua API is still in the server but the preferred way to query for data is using the new ActiveRecord-style query interface in the Ruby gem.
Check out the &lt;a href="/docs/query.html"&gt;Behavioral Query Language&lt;/a&gt; docs for more information.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A flexible command line data importer has been added.
It can load CSV and tab-delimited formats into the database using a simple transform definition.
JSON and server log formats will be added in the near future.
You can find out more about how to use it by looking at the &lt;a href="/docs/import.html"&gt;Bulk Importing Data&lt;/a&gt; docs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;#39;s Next&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next version of Sky will include additional query and importer features.
Also expect to see the Sky front-end called &lt;strong&gt;Skybox&lt;/strong&gt; being released in the near future.
It&amp;#39;ll give you the ability to explore the behavior of your users with an easy to use web-based interface.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sky v0.2.1 Released</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/sky-v0-2-1.html"/>
    <id>/blog/sky-v0-2-1.html</id>
    <published>2013-01-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-01-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;#39;s New?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sky version 0.2.1 has been released.
You can download it from the main &lt;a href="/"&gt;Sky web site&lt;/a&gt;.
There are a lot of features that make data analysis easier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Lua API has been simplified so you just have to implement an &lt;code&gt;aggregate()&lt;/code&gt; method instead of a &lt;code&gt;map()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;reduce()&lt;/code&gt; method.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;#39;s New?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sky version 0.2.1 has been released.
You can download it from the main &lt;a href="/"&gt;Sky web site&lt;/a&gt;.
There are a lot of features that make data analysis easier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Lua API has been simplified so you just have to implement an &lt;code&gt;aggregate()&lt;/code&gt; method instead of a &lt;code&gt;map()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;reduce()&lt;/code&gt; method.
You can see examples of this througout the &lt;a href="/docs"&gt;docs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Session support has been added!
Now you can demarcate sessions by idle time so you can do event analysis in the context of a session.
You can read about it on the &lt;a href="/docs/session.html"&gt;Aggregating Sessions&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://github.com/benbjohnson/bandicoot"&gt;Bandicoot&lt;/a&gt; crash reporting library has been added to the server.
If you experience crashes with Sky then please copy and paste the crash report and &lt;a href="https://github.com/skydb/sky/issues"&gt;submit a ticket on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Added a &lt;code&gt;SkyDB.ping()&lt;/code&gt; method to the Ruby API to check whether the server is up and running. (Thanks &lt;a href="https://github.com/emiddleton"&gt;@emiddleton&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;#39;s Next&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting in mid-January I&amp;#39;ll be leaving my job to start a company called Skyland Labs that is devoted to the development of Sky.
Expect to see a lot more activity on the project going forward.
2013 will be an exciting year for Sky.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sky v0.2.0 Released</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/sky-v0-2-0.html"/>
    <id>/blog/sky-v0-2-0.html</id>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2012-12-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;#39;s New?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sky version 0.2.0 has been released.
You can download it from the main &lt;a href="/"&gt;Sky web site&lt;/a&gt;.
A lot has gone into this release but there are a few areas that are especially important:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[LuaJIT][] has been integrated so you can now run map/reduce across your data on the fly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;#39;s New?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sky version 0.2.0 has been released.
You can download it from the main &lt;a href="/"&gt;Sky web site&lt;/a&gt;.
A lot has gone into this release but there are a few areas that are especially important:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://luajit.org/"&gt;LuaJIT&lt;/a&gt; has been integrated so you can now run map/reduce across your data on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://code.google.com/p/leveldb/"&gt;LevelDB&lt;/a&gt; replaced the previous data store.
LevelDB is a solid key-value store that was written by the famous Googlers, Jeff Dean and Sanjay Ghemawat.
I originally wrote Sky with a custom in-memory data store for performance.
However, after some testing with LevelDB I found that the performance cost could be amortized and Sky is still crunching tens of millions of events per second per core.
Not too shabby.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sky now compiles without warnings on Ubuntu &amp;amp; GCC.
I&amp;#39;m also working on testing other Linux distributions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stability was a big focus with this release as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What&amp;#39;s Next&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the next month I&amp;#39;ll be working on an analytics front-end called Skybox.
You can watch the &lt;a href="https://github.com/skydb/skybox"&gt;repository on GitHub&lt;/a&gt; if you want to follow along.
Skybox will be a Sinatra application that gives you a framework for working with behavioral data analysis.
It will have some built-in visualizations but also let you easily extend it for your needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check it out if you&amp;#39;re interested in seeing some advanced &lt;a href="http://d3js.org/"&gt;D3.js&lt;/a&gt; visualization or if you have some behavioral data you want to crunch and understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expect a Sky v0.3.0 release soon after that as well.
Skybox will be integrating some machine learning and predictive analytics so I&amp;#39;ll be adding other workflows and pipelining to the Lua processing besides map/reduce.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sky Roadmap 2012</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/sky-roadmap-2012.html"/>
    <id>/blog/sky-roadmap-2012.html</id>
    <published>2012-11-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2012-11-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Project Status&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sky has come a long way this past year: It saw its first official v0.1.0
release. A custom query language called Qip was written for it (and then
removed). And finally, multicore distribution was added to allow linear
scalability on each core.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Project Status&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sky has come a long way this past year: It saw its first official v0.1.0
release. A custom query language called Qip was written for it (and then
removed). And finally, multicore distribution was added to allow linear
scalability on each core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that begs the question, what’s next for Sky?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Rest of the Year&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sky is still an early project so I’m not making projections too far out.
However, there are still some awesome features coming down the pipe for
the rest of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, Sky will be adding Lua support via the &lt;a href="http://luajit.org/"&gt;LuaJIT&lt;/a&gt; project. LuaJIT
is an awesome project that allows for dynamic scripting that is compiled
down to machine code at runtime. It’s widely recognized as one of the
fastest dynamic languages available and allows for direct interface with
C code and data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I’m going to be starting an open source analytics project using
Rails that is backed by Sky. You can think of it as an open source
version of &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/analytics/"&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://mixpanel.com/"&gt;MixPanel&lt;/a&gt;. Those are both awesome
products but unfortunately you give up a lot of flexibility and
ownership of your data when you use them. There are some open source
tools available such as &lt;a href="http://piwik.org/"&gt;Piwik&lt;/a&gt; but they only provide basic hit
counters for your pages. With the speed and flexibility of Sky, I
believe you can do powerful analytics like funnel analysis, cohort
analysis and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Suggestions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d love to hear some suggestions as to what other features you’d like
to see in Sky or the new Sky analytics tool. There are also tentative
plans for &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/p/v8/"&gt;V8&lt;/a&gt; to query using JavaScript and &lt;a href="http://julialang.org/"&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt; to query using
statistical computing. Feel free to add a comment below or e-mail the
mailing list at &lt;a href="mailto:sky@librelist.com"&gt;sky@librelist.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>GitHub Archive Visualizer</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/blog/github-archive-visualizer.html"/>
    <id>/blog/github-archive-visualizer.html</id>
    <published>2012-10-17T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2012-10-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;#39;m releasing code and a video for the first &lt;a href="/"&gt;Sky&lt;/a&gt; demo app.
Sky is built to aggregate user actions and state over time so I wanted to find a data set and a visualization that fellow developers would relate to.
And so was born: &lt;strong&gt;The GitHub Archive Visualizer!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;#39;m releasing code and a video for the first &lt;a href="/"&gt;Sky&lt;/a&gt; demo app.
Sky is built to aggregate user actions and state over time so I wanted to find a data set and a visualization that fellow developers would relate to.
And so was born: &lt;strong&gt;The GitHub Archive Visualizer!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="row"&gt;
  &lt;div class="span4"&gt;
    The visualizer uses Sky to step through aggregate paths of user actions.
    So you can walk through and see what users do immediately following an action such as &lt;code&gt;Create Repository&lt;/code&gt;.
    The &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sankey_diagram"&gt;Sankey diagram&lt;/a&gt; shows the total number of users who performed each particular path.
    It&amp;rsquo;s also interactive so you can drill down to as many levels deep as you want.
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
  &lt;div class="span4" style="margin:10px 0px"&gt;
    &lt;a class="thumbnail" href="/images/github-archive-visualizer/githubarchiveviz.png"&gt;
      &lt;img src="/images/github-archive-visualizer/githubarchiveviz_thumb.png"&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s important to note that all the results are computed in real-time.
There&amp;#39;s no aggregation happening.
Every click on the UI recomputes the entire dataset.
In the demo, Sky maxes out at about &lt;strong&gt;60MM events per second&lt;/strong&gt;.
That&amp;#39;s fast enough to crunch through the &lt;a href="http://highscalability.com/blog/2011/3/3/stack-overflow-architecture-update-now-at-95-million-page-vi.html"&gt;monthly pages views of StackOverflow&lt;/a&gt; in about a second and a half.
On my laptop.
On a single thread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Video Walkthrough&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sky is built to import a lot of events per second but to only allow a handful of large queries at a time.
That&amp;#39;s typically how analytics are used within organizations.
The downside of this is that putting a public demo up and having tens of thousands of people querying tens of millions of events each is just not feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I created a short walkthrough of the demo app that you can view below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="row" style="margin:18px 0"&gt;
  &lt;div class="span6 offset1"&gt;
    &lt;a target="_blank" href="https://vimeo.com/51629936"&gt;&lt;img src="/images/github-archive-visualizer/video_thumb.png"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video is six and a half minutes but the first half is a short history on Sky and some information on the dataset.
If you don&amp;#39;t have time to spare, you can skip to 3:20 to actually see the visualizer in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Installing the Demo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the video does satisfy you need for data crunching, you can install the app locally on your machine.
The &lt;a href="https://github.com/skydb/sky-d3-demo"&gt;sky-d3-demo project&lt;/a&gt; project on GitHub has details on how to get up and running.
If you have any issues getting it installed, feel free to add an &lt;a href="https://github.com/skydb/sky-d3-demo/issues"&gt;issue on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll be adding more demos in the future.
If you have any suggestions for behavioral analytics you&amp;#39;d like to see (like &lt;em&gt;dynamic cohort analysis&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;predictive behavioral analytics&lt;/em&gt;), add a comment below to suggest it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Special Thanks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demo wouldn&amp;#39;t be possible without these awesome tools and services:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.githubarchive.org/"&gt;The GitHub Archive&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://www.igvita.com/"&gt;Ilya Grigorik&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://d3js.org/"&gt;D3.js Visualization Library&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://bost.ocks.org/mike/"&gt;Mike Bostock&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
